<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of conformity to the liturgy of the Church of England. In a letter, written to A person of quality, wherein satisfaction is given to certain queries suggested by a non-conformist.</title>
            <author>P. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077592</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077592</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151684</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92566)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151684)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2272:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of conformity to the liturgy of the Church of England. In a letter, written to A person of quality, wherein satisfaction is given to certain queries suggested by a non-conformist.</title>
                  <author>P. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 7-56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Stephen Bulkley and are to be sold by Richard Lambert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: P.S.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: University College Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151684:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF CONFORMITY TO THE LITURGY Of the Church of ENGLAND. In a Letter, Written to a <hi>Perſon of Quality,</hi> wherein ſatisfaction is given to certain Queries ſuggeſted by a Non-Conformiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>YORK,</hi> Printed by <hi>Stephen Bulkley</hi> And are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Lambert,</hi> 1668.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:151684:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Joh. Garthwait,</hi> Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimo in Chriſto Patri, ac Dom. Dom. <hi>Richardo</hi> Archiepiſ. <hi>Eboracenſi,</hi> à Sacris Domeſticis.</signed>
               <dateline>Datum, <hi>Epiſcopo-Thorpae,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb. 19. 1668.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="queries">
            <pb facs="tcp:151684:2"/>
            <head>Queries of a <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHether our Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, as he is God and Man, he not the ſole, Supream Legiſlator to his Church and People in things concerning the Worſhip of God; inſomuch, that what ever externall exhibition of the Worſhip of God, as to the whole, or ſuch part of it as was not in uſe in the Prophets, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours, the Apoſtles dayes, not for above three hundred years after our Lords Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, neither is any where in the ſacred Scriptures appointed by our Lord &amp; Maſiers command, or example to be uſed in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and is ſo far from having his Royall
<pb facs="tcp:151684:3"/>Stamp upon it, that as to ſome parts of it, it is plainly inſufficient (conſidered as a means) to effect that which it is appointed for? whether ſuch a Publick Worſhip of God, with 'its Liturgie, and Rubrick, ought at all to be uſed in the Churches of Chriſt in theſe dayes of Reformation, or Reſtoration of Conformity?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Whether the enjoyments of ſuch a Publick Worſhip, <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> with that ſtrictneſs, that unleſs that Worſhip be uſed, there muſt not be any other Worſhip of God be uſed, be it never ſo Scripturall, and Orthodox? whether this be not a making this Worſhip an Eſſentiall part of Gods Worſhip, and an adding to Gods Word, ſo ſolemnly forbidden in <hi>Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> and <hi>Revelation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Whether if I aſſent, and conſent to the uſe of that Worſhip, Liturgie, and Rubrick? Whether I doe not ſo far ſet up an other Power in co-ordination to my Law-giver, and Judge, who is both God and Man? Yea, Whether I doe not ſet
<pb facs="tcp:151684:3"/>up another Power above Him, if I doe as that Power enjoynes, rather omit, or curtall that I know for certaine my Lord and Maſter enjoynes, than leave one word un-read of that manner of Worſhip a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Power enjoynes? Whether thus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is not ſuch a pleaſing of Man, as declares I am no true ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Whether it be not a tranſgreſsion of my Commiſsion given me by my Lord and Maſters own mouth, in <hi>Mat. 28. ult.</hi> and <hi>penult?</hi> whether it be not in ſome ſence a bidding him keep his Gifts, and Spirit he hath promiſed, keep them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, I am furniſhed with a manner of Worſhip which I can carry on, without his, or his Spirits help, or any extraordinary gift?</p>
            <p>Whether by Aſſenting, and Conſenting, <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> I doe not incurr the curſe threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt Adding, or detracting from the Word of God, and from the word of
<pb facs="tcp:151684:4"/>that Prophet ſpoken of by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Paul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether by Aſſenting, and Conſenting, <hi>ut ſupra,</hi> I doe not recidivate from being a faithfull Witneſs and Aſſerter of my Lord and Maſter his ſole Supremacy, <hi>ut ſupra?</hi> And whether I doe not hereby render my ſelfe plainely without excuſe, when he, at that great day, ſhall ſay, Who required the Exhibition of ſuch a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at thy hands?</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151684:4"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Intended, before this time, to have performed my promiſe to your Ladyſhip, in ſending you a word or two concerning that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which a Divine preſented to your Mother. I told you at <hi>Horn— by Caſtle,</hi> that much having been written by Learned Men of our <hi>Church</hi> concerning this Argument, (which it is ſuppoſed any Miniſter in this Nation, that deſires cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to imploy his Talent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in his native Country to Gods glory, and his Country-mens advantage, will not neglect to peruſe) the beſt courſe would be for a Perſon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151684:5"/>after the Reading of ſuch Writings, (<hi>Hookers Eccleſiaſticall Politie,</hi> Arch-biſhop <hi>Whitgifts Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to the Admonition, Maſons Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of Conformity, Biſhop Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Preface, &amp;c.</hi>) to debate mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters calmely with ſome Divine of a contrary perſwaſion, eſpecially with ſome Learned Biſhop, who by verball conference may poſſibly give the diſſenting perſon that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, which by Reading he cannot yet procure: If (till op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity offer it ſelfe of better aſſiſtance) any weak endeavours of mine might contribute any thing to the ſettlement of this Gentleman, I ſhould be very ready to communicate unto him the ground of my own ſubmiſſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151684:5"/>to the <hi>Church Government</hi> now eſtabliſhed among us, and to hear him produce the Reaſons of his diſſatisfaction: If he ſhall be able by any convincing Arguments to prove, that our Church enjoyneth any thing contrary to the will of the Supreme <hi>Legiſlator,</hi> I hope that nothing that I enjoy at this time in it, ſhall be an impediment unto me of embracing his convictions, and bearing a part of that Croſs, which many of his perſwaſion would have the world think, that they take upon them for the cauſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>'Tis poſſible the Gentleman may have more to alledge in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, than he has expreſſed by writing; otherwiſe I much mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151684:6"/>why he ſhould think him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe warranted to ſuſpend his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of ſuch gifts as God hath given him, and the purſuit of that high Calling, unto which I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him Legally advanced, by reaſon of the preſent ſettlement of our Church.</p>
            <p>For firſt, (in reference to his firſt Querie) We all readily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our Lord Chriſt the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, and ſole <hi>Law-giver</hi> to his Church in all the <hi>ſubſtantialls</hi> of his worſhip and ſervice: But yet we deny that it doth hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that no <hi>circumſtances</hi> of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God are left to the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the preſent Church. The holy Scriptures are a ſufficient rule of Faith, and manners; and we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151684:6"/>abhorr that diſtinction of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> of the Word of God, into <hi>Traditionall</hi> and <hi>Written.</hi> We cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully beleeve all things neceſſary for us to beleeve, and doe, to be contained in thoſe holy Books of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the ſixth Article of our Church: And yet when God was pleaſed to afford us the ſuccour of ſupernaturall Revelation, in the grand Myſteries of our ſalvation, We do not beleeve that he forbad us the ſober uſe of Reaſon; the giving a greater light was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the extinction of the leſſer, but to offer unto us the help of Divine aſſiſtance, in things that naturall reaſon is altogether blind in; the eye of humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151684:7"/>is dimme in diſcerning <hi>naturall</hi> and <hi>Morall</hi> things; altogether blind in <hi>Divine.</hi> We give there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no licence at all unto reaſon, to contradict the revealed will of God in his Word. The ſacred au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority therefore of <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> truth being advanced to that pitch of unqueſtionable dignity, that where it ſpeaks clearly, there no exceptions of Men, or Angels are permitted to interpoſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole what is there ſpoken; what ſhould hinder a ſingle Perſon as far as his liberty is not reſtrained by his Superiours? much leſs a <hi>Nationall Church</hi> publiquely to manage the worſhip of God, after thoſe <hi>Methods,</hi> which reaſon, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by Divine light ſhall judge
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151684:7"/>moſt advantagious for the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Chriſtian Aſſemblies? Doth not our Saviour ask the <hi>Jews, Why, even of themſelves, they did not judge what was right?</hi> Luk. 12.57. And doth not S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> ſend us to the School of nature, to learne, what <hi>haire</hi> beſt becomes the <hi>Maſculine Sex?</hi> 1 Cor. 11.14. What then, though there be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſs precept, or example for that <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which is now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon the Miniſters of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> in the Writings of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or <hi>Prophets?</hi> Muſt we preſently judge our <hi>conformity</hi> unto it unwarrantable, though no ſound Reaſon can be confronted unto it, either in the <hi>Bulk,</hi> or in the <hi>Parcels?</hi> What Argument can
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151684:8"/>Reaſon produce, why the people of God being aſſembled together, the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſhould not compoſe their thoughts to lowly <hi>reverence,</hi> and <hi>penitentiall devotion</hi> by ſome of thoſe pertinent Sentences of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, wherewith our <hi>Liturgy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins? What reaſon can be urged, why an humble <hi>Confeſſion</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately following, a comfortable <hi>Abſolution</hi> ſhould not be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by them, to whom the power of the <hi>Keyes</hi> is committed, and whoſe very <hi>Orders</hi> were given them, with thoſe words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Receive thou the holy Ghoſt; Whoſe ſins thou remitteſt? &amp;c.</hi> Can well enlightned reaſon pleade any juſt cauſe why a competent porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> ſhould not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low?
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151684:8"/>and then <hi>Leſſons</hi> out of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtaments,</hi> with <hi>Hymnes</hi> between, either out of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or conformable unto them? The rehearſall of the <hi>Creed</hi> ſtanding, one would think could offend no man, that ſees every <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticle</hi> founded on Divine authority if he be reſolved to ſtand to his Faith. And the <hi>Antiphones,</hi> or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſes</hi> of the people, if they have not ſufficient grounds from the Hymns of <hi>Moses,</hi> and the Anſwer of <hi>Miriam,</hi> in the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Exod.</hi> and the Song of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak Judg.</hi> 5. Nor the ſinging of the people by courſe, <hi>Ezra</hi> 3.11. yet are as ancient as <hi>Greg. Nazianzen</hi> To be ſure, if the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of Saint <hi>James,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151684:9"/>ſhould be granted to be ſpurious. Nay, <hi>Pliny,</hi> in that famous Letter of his to <hi>Trajan,</hi> ſaith, That the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> did, <hi>Carmen Chriſto quaſi Deo dicere ſecum invicem:</hi> that is, <hi>Sing an Hymn to Chriſt, as a God, by courſe.</hi> This could not be long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Johns</hi> time, for he lived (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierom</hi> writes) to the Reigne of <hi>Trajan.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Baſil</hi> the great lived in the fourth <hi>Century,</hi> about the 70<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. year; and he mentions a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of</hi> devotion, conſiſting of <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternate Verſicles,</hi> as appears by his 63. <hi>Epistle</hi> to the Church of <hi>Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeſarea; The people</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with us, riſeth betimes, after night, to the houſe of Prayer, and making Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God with pains, and tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and diſtreſs of tears; at length,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151684:9"/>riſing from Prayers, fall to Singing of Pſalmes;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that is, <hi>And now being divided into two parts, they Sing by courſe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering one another, thereby both cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborating the meditation of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracles, and adminiſtring to themſelves attention, and indiſtracted vigilancy of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this was no private <hi>Institution</hi> of his own Church, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from what he preſently ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes in the ſame <hi>Epistle, If for this cauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ye forſake us, ye will, together with us, forſake the</hi> Egyptians, <hi>ye will forſake the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of both the</hi> Libia's, <hi>the</hi> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151684:10"/>Paleſtines, Arabians, Phaeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, Syrians, <hi>and thoſe that live upon the River</hi> Euphrates, <hi>and in a word all, amongſt whom watching, and ſupplications, and common Pſalmody are in requeſt.</hi> If it be urged, that none of theſe things were in uſe before three hundred years after our Lords Aſcention, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appeareth from the fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Epistle</hi> of <hi>Pliny;</hi> and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, it may be replyed, that ſome of them were in uſe more than three times 300. years before his birth; for the 92. <hi>Pſalme</hi> is a ſet forme appointed for the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, as it appears by the <hi>Title;</hi> and how well our Saviour, that had the Spirit without meaſure, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved thoſe Formes, to which the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151684:10"/>Synagogue was accuſtomed, may appeare, by his uſe of them in his Agony, and Paſſion. For he was pleaſed to expreſs himſelfe twice in the words of two <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> as is evident, by comparing the 22. <hi>Pſ. ver.</hi> 1. with the 27. of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Mat. ver.</hi> 46. and the 31. <hi>Pſalme, ver.</hi> 5. with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Luke</hi> 23. <hi>ver.</hi> 46. ſo that our late <hi>Annotator</hi> on the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> hath duly hence inferred, <hi>That no Tongue of Men, or Angels, can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a greater heighth of Encomium, to ſet out the honour of any Writing, or give us more reaſon to lay up in our minds the words of the Martyr</hi> Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politus, <hi>That in the dayes of Anti-Chrict,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is, <hi>Liturgie ſhall he extinguiſhed,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151684:11"/>Pſalmody ſhall ceaſe, Reading of the Scriptures ſhall not be heard. In which three, as the publick Service of God,</hi> was by <hi>the Ancients thought</hi> to conſiſt; <hi>ſo the destroying of all, and each of them, must needs be a branch, if not the whole body of Anti-Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſme, a direct contradiction to Christ, who by his preſcription, or practice of each of theſe, imprest a ſacred Character on each.</hi> See Dr. <hi>Hammonds Preface</hi> on the <hi>Pſalmes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this it appears how remote from <hi>Truth</hi> that ſpeech of the <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rist</hi> is, <hi>That our Liturgie is ſo farr from having our Lords Royall Stamp upon it, that is is plainly inſufficient, (conſidered as a means) to effect that for which it is appointed.</hi> For the deſignes of the <hi>Liturgie</hi> are to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151684:11"/>on the worſhip of God, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing ſet <hi>Formes</hi> of <hi>Prayſes, Thanksgivings, and Celebration of the Sacraments, &amp;c.</hi> in ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent method of devotion, as may become the ſolemne Worſhip of that great God, to whom no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is to be preſented, but that which is reaſonable: The repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative body of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> hath thought this <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> now enjoyned, ſuitable to theſe ends; if any particular member think otherwiſe, <hi>Reaſons</hi> ſhould be alledged, not <hi>bold aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Dictator-like</hi> concluded.</p>
            <p>What the <hi>Querist</hi> means, when he asketh <hi>Wether ſuch a Publick Worſhip of God, with 'its Liturgie, and Rubrick, ought at all to be uſed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151684:12"/>in the Churches of Christ in theſe dayes of Reformation, or Restoration of Conformity,</hi> I can ſcarce under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. The <hi>Liturgie</hi> is the ſame, in effect, that it was at the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, that happily was brought to paſs by the pious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of our Anceſtors, in King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th. King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th. and Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes; If any thing contrary to Gods Word, and diſagreeable to the Judgement of the Church Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall be delivered, and enjoyned to be aſſented, and conſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in the <hi>Bulk</hi> of this <hi>Liturgie,</hi> 'tis not, I confeſs, fitting for dayes of <hi>Reformation,</hi> for it will carry 'its <hi>deformation</hi> manifeſtly in thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <hi>corruptions.</hi> But becauſe no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151684:12"/>particular inſtances are alledged, wherein the unſoundneſs of the <hi>Liturgie</hi> doth appear, I beleeve this to be nothing, but a raſh ſurmiſe, voyd of all firme foundation, to pitch a foot on. The Book hath been ſifted, and ſearched over, and over; and when the <hi>Claſſicall Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, that were not ſo mad as to caſt off all ſet Formes, oppoſed themſelves againſt that Forme, that was Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally in force, that is, for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the Forme that is now Ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted amongſt our ſelves, they were quickly convinced, that the fault was rather in their own <hi>intemperate heate,</hi> than in any errors reteined in the <hi>Service Book.</hi> They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained (foure <hi>Claſſes</hi> of them) to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151684:13"/>the Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> ('tis poſſible, that <hi>Aſſent,</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> were too hard meat for their <hi>ſqueaſie Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs:</hi>) That Lord enquired, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would have all Liturgie taken away?</hi> They ſaid, <hi>No.</hi> He required them to make a better, that might take place, upon the removall of what was ſettled. The firſt <hi>Claſſis</hi> framed one, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with the <hi>Genevah Forme.</hi> This the ſecond diſliked, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in 600. particulars. That again had the hard fortune to be quarrel'd by the third <hi>Claſſis:</hi> And what the third reſolved on, by the fourth: And (as a Learned man ſaith) <hi>The diſſenting of thoſe Brethren, as the diviſion of Tongues at</hi> Babel, <hi>was a faire means for keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151684:13"/>that Tower then, from advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any higher.</hi> Vide, <hi>Vindication of the Liturgie,</hi> pag. 3.4.</p>
            <p>What the Gentleman means, <hi>by dayes of Restoring Conformity,</hi> I can but adventure to <hi>divine,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that there was a Clauſe in the beginning of the <hi>Scotch Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> (illegally impoſed by men in uſurped power, and taken, <hi>raſhly</hi> by the ignorant, becauſe they thought it lawfull; and <hi>cowardly</hi> by the fearfull, that loved their integrity leſs than their temporall concernes) wherein the <hi>Covenanter</hi> engageth, <hi>To endeavour the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Word of God, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151684:14"/>of the best Reformed Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</hi> Perhaps the <hi>Querist</hi> hath ſome Church in his eye, unto which we cannot be conformable, whilſt our <hi>Liturgie</hi> ſhall ſtand in force; had he named that Church, we might have enquired, whether our <hi>Church</hi> hath not as good Reaſon, to be <hi>exemplary</hi> to it, as to tread after it. They that have travel'd in this enquiry, will tell us, That they judge the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be the <hi>Eldest Daughter</hi> in all the boundaries of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> and as Orthodox for <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> as any Church, ſince the firſt Ages. Mr. <hi>Durel,</hi> who was Miniſter above eight years in a Proteſtant Church of <hi>France,</hi> will aſſure this Queriſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151684:14"/>
               <hi>That in</hi> France, <hi>and</hi> Genevah, <hi>ſet Formes are enjoyned.</hi> That a <hi>Tigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> Miniſter was queſtioned at <hi>Genevah</hi> for officiating in the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Church there, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſing (as 'tis appointed) the <hi>Creed,</hi> after the Morning Service. The ſame Perſon afore-named, now Miniſter of the <hi>French</hi> Church at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> relates a paſſage of a Letter ſent to him, by the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and eloquent Mounſier <hi>Martell;</hi> the words in Engliſh are theſe, <hi>I wonder to heare, that ſome are found in</hi> England, <hi>that are altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe from any ſet Formes of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, to be obſerved generally one, and the ſame in all the Kingdome; among us, it is no where permitted, to reject the uſe of the Liturgie,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151684:15"/>which was made by</hi> Calvin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed for <hi>Calvins</hi> Liturgy, we leave it to thoſe that like it. But his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for a <hi>Liturgie</hi> are ſo binding, that I know not what can be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged more convincing. Theſe are his words in our Tongue, which he Wrote in a <hi>Latine</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Protector</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his dayes: <hi>As touching the Forme of Prayers, and Ceremonies of the Church, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove very much, that it be Set; and that it be not lawfull for the Miniſters to recede from it in their Function, as well to help the ſimplicity, and unskilfulneſs of ſome, as that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of all the ſeverall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations may appeare: And finally that the deſultory, and capricious
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151684:15"/>lightneſs of ſuch as affect Novelties, may be encountred, and ſtopped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Gentlemans ſecond Querie is, <hi>Whether the Injunction of that Worſhip, to the excluſion of all els, unleſs that be uſed, be not to make it an eſſentiall part of Gods Worſhip, and an</hi> adding <hi>to Gods Word, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in</hi> Deuteronomy, <hi>and the</hi> Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation?</p>
            <p>To Preach God Word, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence his Sacraments; to make Prayers, Supplications, and give thanks for all men, are <hi>Eſſentiall</hi> parts of Gods Worſhip. But to performe theſe duties, after ſuch a <hi>manner,</hi> at ſuch <hi>Forms</hi> of words, and with ſuch <hi>Veſtments,</hi> are but <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantialls,</hi> left in the power of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151684:16"/>the Church, by that generall rule of <hi>St. Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.10. <hi>Let</hi> all <hi>things be done decently, and in order.</hi> I would faine ſee this, or any other perſon, pretending the pleas here alledged, undertake the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the Service of God in ſuch a <hi>Scripturall</hi> manner, that might ſecure him, againſt as ſtrong exceptions, nay far ſtronger, than are here made againſt the Publique Liturgy by this Queriſt.</p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe he would come into the Aſſembly clad with ſome gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or other. For (though <hi>Saul</hi> Propheſied naked; and the <hi>Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> think it their perfection to appear at their Meetings <hi>unappar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled,</hi> yet) few are ſo <hi>Fanatick</hi> as to think thoſe examples obliging
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151684:16"/>others to a conformity. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not approve a <hi>Surplice,</hi> perhaps; May not another pleade as much againſt a <hi>Gowne,</hi> or <hi>Cloak,</hi> or <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſock:</hi> If a white Surplice be no where commanded, neither is a black Gowne; If not to kneele at the Communion, neither to ſit, or ſtand, is a precept in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Text. If the eſtabliſhed Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church are not to be received, becauſe they are no where commanded by expreſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of Scriptures; the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts to the Church muſt permit us, to be ſuch to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, untill they can act upon the warranty of that Word, which they ſay gives no allowance to us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151684:17"/>
But let us heare how the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God muſt be carried on when the Congregation is met; Although the Common Prayers may not be uſed, perhaps becauſe a Forme; perhaps becauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; yet I ſuppoſe the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt would pray after his own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion. If the Service be a Forme, ſuch will be his to thoſe that are to joyne with him: And if it be urged, that by the contrivance of his Forme, his gifts are exerciſed: May I not reply, that theſe are the gifts of the Church in the Prayers authorized by our Governours. The Church forbids no man the imployment of his Talents. At their Ordination, all Miniſters are very powerfuly exhorted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151684:17"/>But we have a cleare Text, That <hi>the Spirits of the Prophets, ought to be ſubject to the Prophets,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.32. That we ought <hi>to obey them that have the rule over us,</hi> Heb. 13.17. That all things ought to be done <hi>decently,</hi> and in <hi>order,</hi> and common ſenſe teacheth us, that where there is no ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, there can be no order. 'Tis certain alſo, that the <hi>Canon</hi> of the Scriptures is ſealed, that no man can pretend to ſuch ſpeciall Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, that what he ſhall utter, muſt conclude the Church as powerfully as if the Prophets, or Apoſtles ſpake. The beſt gifts in men, not exempted from carnall infirmities, may be abuſed. One may be zealous, and want know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151684:18"/>another may be compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently knowing, and want humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. <hi>Ambition,</hi> and <hi>Covetouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Pride,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> have ſtained the gifts of many, in our late remembrance, that might otherwiſe have done (though not ſo much ſervice to the Church as themſelves ſuppoſed) yet leſs miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe than through their miſ-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment ſhe hath ſuſtained. By reaſon of theſe defects, what hath our Church ſuffered? whilſt one was for a <hi>Claſſis;</hi> Another for a gathered <hi>Congregation;</hi> A third againſt <hi>Paedobaptiſme;</hi> A fourth againſt <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and yet all (would we credit them) for <hi>Chriſt.</hi> When theſe had Preached their ſeverall <hi>Sentiments,</hi> they concluded
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151684:18"/>their Harangues with Prayers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to their reſpective judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and the Auditors that heard them muſt either with their <hi>Amen</hi> to ſuch wild <hi>devotions,</hi> ſeal <hi>contradictions,</hi> or ſtand upon their guard, to pick and chooſe, where to joyne <hi>iſſue</hi> with thoſe incohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>ejaculations,</hi> which (in defiance of all Authority of the ancient Church) muſt be obtruded upon the world, as the <hi>Dictates</hi> of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But 'tis alledged, That to enjoyn a ſet <hi>Forme,</hi> ſo as not to ſuffer any parts of Gods worſhip to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on without it, though never ſo Scripturall, ſeems to make an addition to Gods Word, forbidden in <hi>Deut.</hi> and the <hi>Rev.</hi> nothing leſs.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151684:19"/>For here 'tis to be noted, that ſome things are abſolutely good, as, <hi>the Love of God, and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, the believing of the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, praying to, and prayſing of God, &amp;c.</hi> And then, ſome things are abſolutely ſinfull, and wicked; as, <hi>all the violations of the Moral Law, and the diſcredit of any thing commended to our beliefe, under paine of damnation.</hi> But then, ſome things are of an indifferent, and middle nature, neither of themſelves obliging us to the uſe, or refuſall of them; but are left unto us, under our Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to be either <hi>forborne,</hi> or <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed,</hi> as our ſelves ſhall think fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, under no reſtrictions, till our Superiours limit us, but that of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151684:19"/>the Apoſtle, <hi>Whether ye eate or drinke, doe all to the glory of God; And let us follow after the things which make for peace, and things wherewith one way edifie another,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.31. Rom. 14.19. of this kind are the <hi>words,</hi> wherein we preſent our ſupplications to God, the <hi>time</hi> when, (the Lords day excepted,) and the <hi>place</hi> where, the <hi>Garments,</hi> in which we Pray unto him: Which <hi>circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> when the <hi>Church</hi> determineth, ſhe is far from intending to make any addition to the ſacred Oracles of Gods Word, or from ſtraighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that liberty, wherewith <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath made us free. For firſt, The Church of <hi>England</hi> hath no ſuch opinion (as ſome of the <hi>Romaniſts</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:151684:20"/>have of the Orders of ſome of their Saints) touching any conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions that ſhe maketh concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the regulating of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; ſhe placeth no neceſſity in them: Indeed ſhe judgeth, that when ſuch Laws are made, they ought to be obeyed upon the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation</hi> of the fifth <hi>Commandement:</hi> But that <hi>obligation</hi> ſprings not from the <hi>immediate Law giver,</hi> but from the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of him, that hath commanded us to ſubmit our ſelves to every Ordinance of Man, for the Lords ſake. For even after her determination, the Church ſuppoſeth the indifferency that was before, ſtill to continue, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the things themſelves; onely in reſpect of uſe, and ſo farr,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151684:20"/>as concerns us, we are under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint; but yet not ſo, that the violation of ſuch Laws, when it falleth to be committed upon ſome ſudden emergency, is eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſin like the breach of Gods Laws, ſo long, as it is without wantonneſs, ſcandall, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Church conceiveth her ſelfe not ſo bound to keep any Rites, or Ceremonies eſtabliſhed, but that upon due motives, ſhe may alter them as ſhe pleaſeth, preſcribing to no other Church, what they ſhould doe, but permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto them, in this behalfe, the liberty that her ſelfe taketh. If upon this ground, it ſhould be inferred, Why are ſuch Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151684:21"/>of which the Church decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth her judgement to be, that in themſelves they are indifferent, preſſed ſo <hi>indiſpenſably,</hi> that he that will not aſſent, and conſent to the uſe of them, muſt not be ſuffered to uſe another manner of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which he conceives more <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturall?</hi> We anſwer, That it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains not to private men to judge what Publick Worſhip is moſt <hi>Scripturall,</hi> but to the <hi>Governors</hi> of the Church; and they think, that the <hi>Liturgy</hi> eſtabliſhed is as <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturall</hi> a Worſhip, as any that can be conteſted againſt it: If the Scriptures had appointed, with what words, and after what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Forme, the whole Service of the Church ſhould have been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151684:21"/>that method would have obliged all Chriſtians; but ſuch a Forme is no where extant in all the Book of God. Indeed there is a generall Rule, <hi>That all things ſhould be done decently, and in Order:</hi> And a cleare Injunction, that we ſhould <hi>obey thoſe that are over us in the Lord,</hi> to whom it belongs to judge what in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Aſſemblyes is decent, and orderly.</p>
            <p>It may be this Queriſt would have every Miniſter of God in the Publique Service of the <hi>Church,</hi> proceed according to the meaſure of his <hi>Talents,</hi> which he ſuppoſeth may be husbanded to the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſoules, far more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly, than the preſcript Formes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151684:22"/>can be, which being <hi>known,</hi> and alwayes the <hi>ſame,</hi> are apt to beget, or at leaſt nouriſh in us <hi>formality, oſcitancy,</hi> and <hi>dulneſs</hi> in thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes, that ſhould be <hi>active,</hi> and <hi>vigorous,</hi> full of <hi>affection,</hi> and <hi>holy zeale.</hi> I know ſuch things have bin pleaded, but experience hath taught us, that neither ſet <hi>Formes</hi> doe neceſſarily beget thoſe evill effects; nor doe the <hi>arbitrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions</hi> of ſuch Divines, as have thought fitting to renounce com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with the rule enjoyned them, provide againſt them. We have no deſire to reproach men; but if we had, might we not tell them, that the new methods of deviſion which entred, upon the late <hi>baniſhment</hi> of the <hi>Liturgie,</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151684:22"/>were ſo far from <hi>ſpiritualizing</hi> the people, that pertook of them, that if <hi>Pride, Contention, Schiſme, Rebellious contumacy againſt Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, both Eccleſiaſticall, and Civill; Oppreſſion and Covetouſneſs,</hi> are works of the fleſh, a more carnall generation of profeſſors cannot be produced, I ſay, not ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, but ſcarce ſince Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, than thoſe that have (upon pretence of <hi>Carnality,</hi> &amp; <hi>Formality</hi>) deſerted the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I hope upon conſideration of what hath already been ſaid, the <hi>Queriſt</hi> may eaſily perceive, that, by his <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent to the Liturgy, &amp;c.</hi> he will not fall under the guilt of ſetting up a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151684:23"/>power in <hi>co-ordination</hi> to our great <hi>Law-giver,</hi> who is God and Man; much leſs need he feare, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſhall advance a power above Chriſt. For the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> pretends to no infallible authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over mens Conſciences, ſhe is farr from checking any thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly commanded by the Spirit of Chriſt, in the Writings of the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> onely by the help of that light, which ſhe thence receiveth, ſhe endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to direct and aſſiſt all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, within her <hi>Communion,</hi> in the moſt ready courſe of performing the duties there required; and herein ſhe recommendeth her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings to the judgement of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans Conſcience, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151684:23"/>no cenſure from any <hi>Church</hi> ſince the Reformation: Nay, ſo far is ſhe from incurring the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the reſt of her <hi>Siſters,</hi> that they rather emulate her <hi>Beauty.</hi> We are aſſured, that the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches which follow the Confeſſion of <hi>Ausburgh,</hi> have the very ſame, both <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> in every particular that we have: Nay, they go farr beyond us in many things of the ſame kind, which our <hi>Church</hi> hath thought fit to lay aſide; and yet, by a <hi>Nationall Aſſembly</hi> of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> held at <hi>Charenton, Anno</hi> 1631. are quitted from the charge, either of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or <hi>Superstition</hi> in their publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. See <hi>Durel, pag.</hi> 4. ſo that, if
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151684:24"/>the <hi>Queriſt,</hi> by his former expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where he mentions, <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of conformity,</hi> would tax our <hi>Church</hi> with <hi>Non-conformity</hi> to the reſt of the Reformation, becauſe ſhe reteineth a <hi>Liturgie,</hi> with a <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick;</hi> he is ſtrangely miſtaken, and knows not the <hi>Methods</hi> of their publick worſhip. For as the moſt of them have a ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Paſtors, and admit not a parity in the Government of their <hi>Churches;</hi> ſo have they (as the cited Author atteſteth) all of them ſet Formes of Prayer, not one excepted; he inſtanceth in the Imperiall Towns, and other Free States, as <hi>Strasburgh, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lm, Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Norenburgh, Hamburg, Lubeck,</hi> and in all the Territories of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151684:24"/>Soveraigne Princes of <hi>Germany, Saxony, Brandenburg, Lawenburg, Brunſwick, Baden, Ouſpatch, Meck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenburg, &amp;c.</hi> ſo that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by aboliſhing <hi>Liturgie,</hi> would be ſo farr from reſtoring conformity with the beſt Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches, that ſhe would be rather <hi>Schiſmaticall,</hi> by walking in a path by her ſelfe alone.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But the <hi>Queriſt</hi> would know, Whether to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to the Forme enjoyned, be not a tranſgreſſion of his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> given him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>ult. &amp; penult.</hi> The Commiſſion there given, was immediately pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Apoſtles, who were to be Chriſts <hi>Witneſſes of what they had heard, and ſeen, by Preaching repentance, and remiſſion of ſins, in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151684:25"/>his Name, among all Nations, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at Jeruſalem,</hi> Luke 24.47, 48. ſo farr, as it extends to all inferiour orders of the Miniſtery, they may well think themſelves concerned to fulfill ſo ſolemne a charge; the words are, <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, Baptizing them, &amp;c. Teaching them to obſerve all things, whatſoever I have commanded you, &amp;c.</hi> I cannot imagine how the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> it no where prohibits the teaching of Chriſts Precepts: and if any in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of our <hi>Nationall Church</hi> ſhall preſume to teach any thing contrary unto them, I hope the care of our <hi>Spirituall Governours</hi> is ſo great, that he would no longer
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151684:25"/>be permitted to proceed in ſowing ſuch tares, than he ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed guilty of ſo foule a crime; neither do the dutifull Sons of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England, bid Chriſt</hi> (as the <hi>Querist</hi> pretends) <hi>keep his gifts and ſpirit which he hath promiſed, to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Nay rather, when they obſerve the ſpirit of <hi>wiſedom</hi> and <hi>counſell,</hi> ſo to have <hi>aſſiſted</hi> the <hi>Compilers</hi> of the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> that the exacteſt ſearchers into it, &amp; diſputers againſt it, have bin able (after all their heats) ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſionately to <hi>revile</hi> it, than ſolidly to <hi>confute</hi> it; they own Chriſts gracious ſuccour in the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination, and direction of thoſe that framed it, and ſee that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall promiſe verified in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the particular <hi>Nationall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151684:26"/>Church,</hi> in the very. Text alledged by the <hi>Querist, Lo I am with you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, even to the end of the world.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Querist</hi> may be ſecure, that his <hi>Aſſenting</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting,</hi> will never endanger him to incurr <hi>the curſe denounced against ſuch as ſhall adde, or detract from the Word of God.</hi> For our <hi>Church</hi> doth not impoſe her <hi>Liturgy</hi> as immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <hi>inſpired,</hi> but contrived <hi>through the aſſistance of the Spirit indeed</hi> but by men, uſing the means of <hi>study;</hi> and <hi>carefull enquiry</hi> after the truth, not challenging <hi>Propheticall,</hi> or <hi>Apostolical infallibility.</hi> Whereupon it will follow, that the <hi>complyer</hi> with this method of Worſhip, can in no reaſon be charged with <hi>reei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divation</hi> from aſſerting Chriſts ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151684:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>for the <hi>Liturgy</hi> controles no Law of Chriſt, nor challengeth any <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to the diminution of his <hi>authority;</hi> but directs us to make all our <hi>addreſſes to God the Father in his name, and glorifieth him as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the unity of the bleſſed Spirit, common to them both,</hi> teaching us, to aſcribe honour, prayſe, obedience, and adoration to the three Perſons in the unity of the ſame eſſence, for ever and ever. He that diſtruſteth the ſettlement of ſo well an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Church, may rather be afraid to incurr the curſe wiſhed by the Apoſtle, upon the <hi>disturbers</hi> of the peace of the <hi>Galatians, I would they were even cut off that trouble you.</hi> Let a man ſearch the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and examine every parcell of it, I am
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151684:27"/>confident that he ſhall find no part of it contrary to ſound reaſon, the <hi>ſacred</hi> Text, or the uſage and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the ancient Church: and then I think S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Augustines</hi> words may be worth the <hi>Querists</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, <hi>Contra rationem nemo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brius, contra Scripturasnemo Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus, contra Eccleſiam nemo pacificus ſenſerit, de Trin.</hi> 4.6. no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man will contradict reaſon, no Chriſtian the Scriptures, no peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able perſon the cuſtome of the Church.</p>
            <p>Good <hi>Madam,</hi> whether I have ſaid enough to ſatisfie the Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of the <hi>Queries,</hi> I know not; but I am confident, that I have ſaid more than was requiſite to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your Ladyſhip, for you are
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151684:27"/>better Principled in the Religion eſtabliſh't amongſt us, than to be ſhaken by ſuch <hi>Propoſals,</hi> as the <hi>Queriſt's</hi> Paper has offered to your conſideration.</p>
            <p>Indeed, it ſeems ſtrange to me, that Perſons (otherwiſe not voyd of common ſenſe) ſhould ſo bungle in diſputes of this nature, as, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſiderable force of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, to oppoſe, not onely the practice of our own <hi>Church,</hi> and all others of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> but to ſlight the precedent of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church,</hi> throughout the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> for a long time before, even impudence it ſelf dare charge them with <hi>Superſtition,</hi> or <hi>Idolatry;</hi> except God in his juſt judgement has given them up unto a ſpirit of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151684:28"/>
               <hi>deluſion:</hi> For it is very poſſible, that they, who upon ſecular deſignes, diſturbed the ſettlement of our <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe prudent, and pious conſtitutions, their own ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions had ſometimes juſtified, ſhould deſervedly be puniſhed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſo much blindneſs, as not to ſee what formerly they diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; or with ſo much hardneſs of heart, as to refuſe to comply with, what they can, with no ſolidity of reaſon, diſapprove and cenſure. The piety and charity of your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip make you zealous to win others to the ſame perſwaſion, which, upon, not onely the <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> but the <hi>convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of your own diſcerning Judgement, you have embraced. I
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151684:28"/>heartily wiſh, that theſe, or any other endeavours of mine might contribute ſomewhat to the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any <hi>diſſenters</hi> to the boſom of that affectionate <hi>Mother,</hi> whom they have ſo deeply, by their Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie, diſquieted, and grieved.</p>
            <p>'Tis not, in my judgement, an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>comprehenſion,</hi> that will ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect this great work, that will but diſparage the <hi>Wiſedome</hi> and <hi>gravity</hi> of our pious <hi>Mother,</hi> and farther confirme ſuch wanton Children (as reſolve never to be confuted) in their <hi>obstinate,</hi> though <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> oppoſitions. It muſt be ſome <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>incomprehenſible</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and power of God, who is able both to illuminate the eyes of the <hi>blind,</hi> and diſcover unto
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151684:29"/>them the path of <hi>Truth,</hi> and to or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the <hi>Footſteps</hi> of the <hi>perverſ</hi> and guide them into the way of <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Chriſtian charity will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline you to implore Almighty God for ſuch a mercy for them, and I ſhall cheerfully joyn with you in the ſame requeſt. To this I ſhall, at this time, adde but one more (for a bleſſing upon your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Perſon, and Family) and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving you any further trouble of Reading what has (long ſince) exceeded the meaſures of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Good Madam,</salute> 
               <signed> Your Ladiſhips humble ſervant in Chriſt, <hi>P. S.</hi>
               </signed>
               <date>Feb. 25. 1667/8.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
